H.K.H. Silk Company Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
H.K.H. Silk Company Records.
1892-1924.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
H.K.H. Silk Company.
4 linear feet.
MSS19990066
Hammond, Knowlton and Company was a silk manufacturer in operation prior to 1892. The company consolidated with other companies in 1918 to form the H.K.H. Silk Company. This company had mills in Putnam, Watertown, New London, and Woodbury, CT, as well as Haverstraw, NY. The company headquarters was in Watertown, CT. In early 1925, it appears that the company changed its name to the Heminway Silk Corporation. As a matter of local interest, it is worth noting that company treasurer Clarence Asahel Hammond-Knowlton resided in Mansfield Center, CT, on Knowlton Hill near Gurleyville Rd.
History
Hammond, Knowlton and Company were silk manufacturers prior to 1892. Key figures in the development of the company were Charles Clark Knowlton and his cousin, George Asahel Hammond. G.A. Hammond served as a member of the Connecticut commission at the 1892 World Columbian Exposition in Chicago, where the company silks were the official silks of the Exposition. The company was awarded a bronze medallion from the Exposition. The collection includes two letters, one from 1894 and the other from 1897, to C.C. Knowlton from G.A. Hammond. In the 1897 letter Hammond refutes questions that have arisen as to his character.
C. C. Knowlton adopted his cousin Clarence Asahel Hammond-Knowlton. C. A. Hammond-Knowlton was also involved with the silk company, and received a patent in 1912 for a “Method of Producing a Filled Bobbin.” By 1921, C. A. Hammond-Knowlton was the treasurer of the H.K.H. Silk Company, the new name for the company having been adopted after some acquisitions around 1918. It appears that the company changed its name to the Heminway Silk Corporation in 1925 to reflect the major brand name of the silk articles being produced by the company.
Scope and Content
The collection contains a few letters and pieces of ephemera, as noted above. However, the bulk of the material in the collection consists of the personal correspondence, both incoming and outgoing, of Clarence Asahel Hammond-Knowlton from the years 1921 to 1924. C. A. Hammond-Knowlton appears to have been chief executive officer for the company at this time (despite the title of treasurer), and it is possible that his father, C. C. Knowlton, was suffering from illness or was unable to carry out all of his responsibilities as president of the company. Correspondence covers a wide range of topics. Some letters address business dealings, and other matters are purely personal. The H.K.H. Silk Company had mills in Putnam, Watertown, New London, and Woodbury, CT, and Haverstraw, NY. The company offices were in Watertown, CT, but C. A. Hammond-Knowlton lived with his wife, Isabel, and his daughter, Mildred, in Mansfield Center, CT, on Knowlton Hill near Gurleyville Road.
Interesting correspondences include those between C. A. Hammond-Knowlton and his father, C. C. Knowlton, those with the Silk Association of America, those with the Connecticut Chamber of Commerce, materials relating to the pollution of a stream in Putnam, Connecticut, by an H.K.H. mill, and personal correspondences from C. A. Hammond-Knowlton relating to his hobby as an early enthusiast of radio.
Arrangement
Collection consists of a single series. Organization is chronological and then alphabetical. Within folders, original arrangements have been retained, with correspondents usually grouped together (chronology within folders is somewhat imprecise).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of records for a number of Connecticut textile businesses, including those of the Cheney Brothers Silk Manufacturing Company, Belding Brothers and Company, Deep River Lace Company, Slater Company, and the Wauregan and Quinebaug Company. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Information in this finding aid compiled by Laura Katz Smith through correspondence with Evelyn Guymon of Tucson, Arizona, and from materials in the collection.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
K.K.H. Silk Company.
Subjects:
Silk industry--Connecticut.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Administrative Records.; Ephemera
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Custodial History
Records from the 1920s were stored on the property of Isabel Atwood of Storrs, CT, and in July 1999.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Evelyn Guymon of Tucson, Arizona in 1999.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence and Ephemera, 1892-1924
  - World Columbian Exposition Medal, 1892 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Letters from G.A. Hammond to C. C. Knowlton, 1894, 1897 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Letter from E.G. Siggers to C.A. Hammond-Knowlton, packet includes patent information (patent held by C.A. Hammond-Knowlton) and supplementary publications on patent rights, 1912-1915 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - C.A. Hammond-Knowlton Correspondence, “A”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, “B”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, “C”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, “D”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, “E-F”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, “G”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, “H”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Haverstraw Dept., 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, “I, J, K”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, C.C. Knowlton, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, “L”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, “M”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, H. M. Merriman, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, “N” through “Q”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, New London Dept., 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, New York Dept., 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, Putnam Dept., 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, “R”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, “S”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, F. W. Shaw, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, Silk Association of America, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, H. G. Stine, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, “T, U, V”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, T. B. Thompson, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, “W” through “Z”, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, Watertown Dept., 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, “A”, 1922 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, “B”, 1922 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, “C”, 1922 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, “D, E”, 1922 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, “F, G”, 1922 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, “I” through “L”, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, J. G. Johnson, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, C. C. Knowlton, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, “M”, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, H. M. Merriman, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, “N” through “P”, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, New York Dept., 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, “R”, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, “S”, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, F. W. Shaw, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, A. A. Smith, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, H. G. Stine, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, “T, U”, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, T. B. Thompson, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, “W” through “Y”, 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, Watertown Dept., 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, “A”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, “Applications”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, “B”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, “Babson's Statistical Reports”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, “C”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence, “D” through “F”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence, “G, H”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence, Haverstraw Dept., 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence, “I” through “L”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence, C. C. Knowlton, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence, “M”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence, H. M. Merriman, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 62)
  - Correspondence, “N, O”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence, New York Dept., 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence, “P” through “R”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence, Benjamin Pomeroy, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 66)
  - Correspondence, Putnam Department, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence, “S”, 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence, A. A. Smith, 1923 (Box 3:, Folder 69)
  - Correspondence, F. W. Shaw, 1923 (Box 3:, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence, H. G. Stine, 1923 (Box 3:, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence, “T, U”, 1923 (Box 3:, Folder 72)
  - Correspondence, T. B. Thompson, 1923 (Box 3:, Folder 73)
  - Correspondence, “V” through “Z”, 1923 (Box 3:, Folder 74)
  - Correspondence, Watertown Dept., 1923 (Box 3:, Folder 75)
  - Correspondence, “A”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 76)
  - Correspondence, “Applications”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 77)
  - Correspondence, “B”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 78)
  - Correspondence, “C”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 79)
  - Correspondence, “D”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 80)
  - Correspondence, “E” through “G”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 81)
  - Correspondence, “H”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 82)
  - Correspondence, Haverstraw Dept., 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 83)
  - Correspondence, “I” through “K”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 84)
  - Correspondence, C. C. Knowlton, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 85)
  - Correspondence, “L”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 86)
  - Correspondence, “M”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 87)
  - Correspondence, H. M. Merriman, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 88)
  - Correspondence, “N, O”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 89)
  - Correspondence, New York Dept., 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 90)
  - Correspondence, “P”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 91)
  - Correspondence, Pollution of Stream Materials, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 92)
  - Correspondence, Benjamin Pomeroy, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 93)
  - Correspondence, Putnam Dept., 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 94)
  - Correspondence, “Q, R”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 95)
  - Correspondence, “S”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 96)
  - Correspondence, F. W. Shaw, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 97)
  - Correspondence, Silk Association of America, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 98)
  - Correspondence, A. A. Smith, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 99)
  - Correspondence, H. G. Stine, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 100)
  - Correspondence, “T” through “V”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 101)
  - Correspondence, T. B. Thompson, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 102)
  - Correspondence, “W” through “Y”, 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 103)
  - Correspondence, Watertown Dept., 1924 (Box 3:, Folder 104)